字幕翻译/压制：旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/Lr_zfpzGxQQ
原视频发布日期：20200524
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
- 嗨 我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
- Hi, it's me Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
NASA给国际空间站运输航天员的新载具是SpaceX的载人龙飞船
NASA has a new ride to the International Space Station for its astronauts and it's SpaceX's Crew Dragon Capsule.
所以我想给你讲一个很短的梗概来说明所有事件的时间
So I wanted to give you a super quick rundown of the exact timing of all the events
也就是发射日那天前往国际空间站的航天员会经历的事情
that a crew heading out to the ISS will go through on launch day,
从穿上宇航服到和空间站对接
all the way from suit up to docking with the station.
那么 我不会去讲解猎鹰9号火箭或者载人龙飞船的细节
Now, we're not going to go over the Falcon 9 rocket or the Crew Dragon Capsule's details.
如果你需要一个类似的概略
If you need a rundown on that,
b23.tv/BV1fb411j7nW
我已经做了相关视频
I've already got a video going into the exact hardware here,
也就是那个把龙飞船和其他商业飞船 波音的星际航线进行比较的视频
comparing it to NASA's other new commercial ride, the Boeing Starliner.
那么 查看简介中那个视频的链接
So check the description for a link to that video
everydayastronaut.com/crew-dragon-timeline/
还有用于以后参考的这个视频的文章版
and an article version of this video for future reference.
好了 让我们开始吧
Okay, let's get started!
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
起飞
and liftoff!
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
发射活动会在倒计时04:59:59开始
- The launch events start at T-minus four hours 59 minutes and 59 seconds,
此时龙飞船将其惯性测量单元进行了校准并进行发射配置
when the Dragon Capsule aligns its inertial measurement units and is configured for launch.
倒计时04:30:00
T-minus four hours and thirty minutes.
载人龙飞船用于反作用力控制推进器的自燃燃料
The Crew Dragon Capsule's hypergolic fuels for reaction control thrusters
和超级天龙座逃逸发动机都开始为发射加压
and the Superdraco abort motors are pressurized for flight.
倒计时04:15:00
T-minus four hours fifteen minutes.
乘员在穿宇航服之前会听一个天气简报
The crew hears a weather briefing before they suit up.
而如果你想要知道发射的标准是什么
And if you wanna know what the criteria is to launch,
就是屏幕上的这个
here it is on-screen,
everydayastronaut.com/crew-dragon-timeline/
但简介里也有一个对应的链接
but we also have a link to this in the description as well,
因为能够顺利发射的天气需要确保很多东西没问题
'cause there's a lot of stuff to make sure that they're good to go for weather.
倒计时04:05:00
T-minus four hours and five minutes.
乘员由NASA转交给SpaceX
The crew is officially handed off from NASA to SpaceX,
这有点儿例行公事 但意味着航天员正式由SpaceX指挥了
which is bit of a formality but signifies the astronauts are officially in SpaceX's hands.
倒计时04:00:00
T-minus four hours.
航天员在肯尼迪航天中心 尼尔阿姆斯特朗出发作业大楼穿上宇航服
The crew suits up at Kennedy Space Center's Neil Armstrong Operations and Checkout Building.
倒计时03:22:00
T-minus three hours and 22 minutes.
乘员离开大楼 接着进入NASA和SpaceX的特斯拉X型乘员运输车中
The crew leaves the building and gets into NASA and SpaceX's Tesla ModelX crew transportation vehicles.
换句话说 在38分钟内 乘员穿上航天服 准备出发
In other words, the crew gets suited up and ready to go in just 38 minutes,
这可比大多数人早上去上班的时间要快
which is faster than most of us get ready for work in the morning.
倒计时03:15:00
T-minus three hours 15 minutes.
乘员离开出发作业大楼
The crew departs the Ops and Checkout building
前往13.6公里外的历史性的发射综合体39A
and heads the 13.6 kilometers, or 8.5 miles, to historic Launch Complex 39A.
倒计时02:55:00
T-minus two hours 55 minutes.
乘员抵达发射台
The crew arrives at the pad.
因为他们花了20分钟走完13.6km
Since they will travel about 13.6 km in 20 minutes,
it means they'll only average around 40 kilometers an hour.
这意味着他们的平均时速只有差不多40km/h
得了吧
Come on!
我是指 他们应该打开狂暴模式 给大家好好秀一秀
I mean, they should turning on ludicrous mode and put on a show for everybody!
倒计时02:40:00左右
T-minus two hours and 40-ish minutes or so.
乘员会最终走进乘员出入臂
The crew will do that ultimate walk across the Crew Access Arm.
那么 希望他们会走出慢动作 这样我们就能得到一些很棒的电影片段
Now, hopefully they'll walk in slow-mo so we get some of that awesome cinematic footage.
倒计时02:35:00
T-minus two hours 35 minutes.
乘员进入龙飞船
The crew enters the Dragon.
倒计时02:20:00
T-minus two hours and 20 minutes.
进行乘员和任务控制中心之间的通信检查
There's a communications check between the crew and the Mission Control.
倒计时02:15:00
T-minus two hours 15 minutes.
座椅转向上方
The seats rotate up,
让航天员更加靠紧椅背 并且离屏幕和控制台更近
putting the astronauts more on their backs and closer to the screens and controls.
Immediately after at T-minus two hours 14 minutes,
紧接着在倒计时02:14:00
他们检查航天服的气密性 并确保能进行发射
they check for leaks in the suits and verify that they're good to go.
倒计时01:55:00
T-minus one hour 55 minutes.
飞船舱门关闭 地面支持人员离开了发射台
The hatch is closed up and the ground support crew leaves the pad.
倒计时01:10:00
T-minus one hour and 10 minutes.
国际空间者的准确状态和位置会上传到龙飞船的导航系统里
The exact state and location of the International Space Station is uploaded to the Dragon Capsule's navigation.
倒计时00:45:00
T-minus 45 minutes.
会投票决定是否进行火箭的燃料加注
The go/no-go poll is taken to fuel up the rocket.
倒计时00:42:00
T-minus 42 minutes.
乘员出入臂收回了
The Crew Access Arm is retracted.
倒计时00:37:00
T-minus 37 minutes.
龙飞船的发射逃逸系统准备完毕
The Dragon Capsule's launch escape system is armed,
这能让乘员在火箭加注过程中或上升过程中进行逃逸
which gives the crew the ability to abort from the rocket if there were a problem during fuel up or during ascent.
倒计时00:35:00
T-minus 35 minutes.
RP-1（精炼煤油）火箭燃料 和低温的液氧开始加注到火箭的一级部分
Both the RP-1 rocket fuel and the cryogenic liquid oxygen begin loading into the first stage of the rocket
而二级的RP-1加注完毕
and the RP-1 is loaded into the second stage.
此时 你会发现火箭看起来有很多烟
It's around this time that you'll notice the rocket begins to look all smokey.
但其实这不是烟
That's not smoke.
那是冰冷的液氧正加注入火箭时产生的冷凝水
That's condensation from the cold, cold liquid oxygen loading into the vehicle.
SpaceX使用的是低达零下207摄氏度的过冷液氧
SpaceX super-chills the liquid oxygen down to -207 degrees Celsius,
但还不足以达到液氧零下219度凝点的温度
which is just shy of the -219 degrees Celsius that would turn the oxygen into a solid.
不过这有助于提高性能和密度
But this helps maximize performance and density.
因为液氧处在相对温暖的火箭里
As the liquid oxygen sits inside the relatively warm rocket,
它会升温并气化
it's going to warm up and boil off into a gas,
这将增加近1000倍体积 并需要排出来
which expands nearly 1,000 times in volume and needs to be vented out.
现在 它仍是非常冷的 当它排泄到大气中时
Now, it's still extremely cold and when it vents out into the atmosphere,
它会因为和空气中的气态水接触（使之液化）而产生许多小的蒸汽云
it's going to create little clouds of condensation due to coming in contact with the humidity in the air.
那么 这是正常的 并说明燃料加注正在进行中
Now, this is normal and it's a good sign that fueling is under way.
倒计时00:16:00
T-minus 16 minutes.
二级液氧开始加注
The liquid oxygen begins filling the second stage.
倒计时00:07:00
T-minus seven minutes.
猎鹰9号开始让液氧流过一级的9台梅林发动机
The Falcon 9 begins to flow liquid oxygen through the nine Merlin engines on the first stage,
让它们适应很快将要流过的推进剂的低温
conditioning them for the cryogenic temperatures of the propellant that will be flowing through them soon.
倒计时00:05:00
T-minus five minutes.
龙飞船转用内部电源
The Dragon Capsule transitions to internal power.
倒计时00:01:00
T-minus one minute.
飞行计算机开始最后的发射前检查 并让储罐加压至飞行压力
The flight computer begins final prelaunch checks and the tanks get pressurized to flight pressure,
也就是3bar
which is three bar.
倒计时00:00:45
T-minus 45 seconds.
SpaceX的发射指挥确认他们会进行发射 同时这也是时候变得兴奋起来了
The SpaceX launch director verifies they are go for launch and it's officially time to get excited!
倒计时00:00:03
T-minus three seconds.
9个梅林发动机点燃并提升到最大推力
The nine Merlin engines ignite and ramp up to full thrust
同时固定装置锁住火箭直到倒计时为0时
while the hold-down clamps hold onto the rocket until T-minus zero.
这给火箭发动机足够的时间在正式发射前来正常运行
This allows enough time to ensure all the engines are performing correctly before committing to the launch.
最后倒计时为零时
And finally at T-minus zero seconds,
固定装置松开 并让猎鹰9号离开发射台
the clamps let go and the Falcon 9 lifts off the pad,
开始其前往国际空间站的19小时的旅程
beginning its 19-hour journey to the International Space Station.
现在 对于验证2任务
Now, for the Demo 2 mission,
这将会是美国第一次载人入轨飞行
it'll be the first time humans leave the Earth from the United States and go to orbit
自航天飞机的最后一次任务STS-135以来
since the Space Shuttle's last mission STS-135,
STS-135在2011年也是于同样的发射台发射
which took off from this exact pad in 2011.
事实上 DM-2的航天员之一
In fact, one of the DM-2 astronauts,
Doug Hurley 就在STS-135上面
Doug Hurley, was on STS-135!
这也太帅了
That is so cool!
火箭加速 垂直上升并摆脱大气层最厚的那部分
The rocket accelerates, ascending vertically to get out of the thickest parts of the atmosphere,
但是很快 它会进行程序转弯并且开始水平加速
but pretty soon it will begin to pitch over and begins to accelerate horizontally.
火箭竖直方向的运动只是为了让它离开大气层
The rocket really only goes up to get out of the atmosphere.
而入轨则需要大量的水平速度
Getting it into orbit requires an awful lot of horizontal velocity,
around 27,000 kilometers an hour.
差不多27000km/h（7.5km/s）的速度
正如我喜欢说的那样 你去太空 要竖着向上走
As I like to say, to get to space you go up;
留在太空 要横着走 而且非常快
to stay in space you go sideways, very, very fast.
发射后58秒
T-plus 58 seconds.
此时火箭遇到了最大气动压力
The rocket encounters maximum aerodynamic pressure,
或者说max-Q
or max Q, which is when the vehicle experiences the strongest aerodynamic forces on it.
在此之后
After this point,
尽管火箭仍然越来越快
despite the rocket still going faster and faster,
空气也将越来越薄 最终几乎是不存在的
the air is also going thinner and thinner and eventually is pretty much non-existent.
发射后2分33秒
T-plus two minutes 33 seconds.
一级火箭发动机关闭
The first stage engines shut down,
或者说主发动机关闭 也称MECO
or main engine cut off occurs, otherwise known as MECO.
T-plus two minutes 36 seconds.
发射后2分36秒
The first stage lets go of the second stage for stage separation.
一二级分离
发射后2分44秒
T-plus two minutes 44 seconds.
二级的单台梅林真空发动机点火
The second stage ignites its single vacuum optimized Merlin engine
并把航天器继续加速到轨道速度
and continues to accelerate the vehicle to orbital velocities.
与此同时 猎鹰9号进行了很独特的机动
At the same time, the Falcon 9 does something super unique.
级间段上的冷气推进器让一级火箭翻转过来
Its first stage flips around using some cold gas thrusters up on its interstage
而最终发动机朝前
and this ends up pointing the engines forward,
准备让火箭以发动机朝前的姿态再入大气层
preparing the vehicle to re-enter the atmosphere engines-first.
与此同时
Now at this moment,
一级仍在向上滑行
the first stage is still coasting upwards,
但几分钟后
but after a few minutes,
它将向下返回地球
it will begin to fall back down to Earth.
差不多发射后2分52秒
At around T-plus two minutes and 52 seconds,
你可能会注意到一个圆环从梅林真空发动机的钟形喷嘴上脱落
you'll likely notice a ring fall off of the bell nozzle of the Merlin vacuum engine.
那么 不要惊慌
Now, don't panic.
这是应该发生的
That's supposed to happen.
这是个软木加强环
That's a cork ring stiffener
让薄薄的铌制喷嘴延伸段保持形状
that holds the thin niobium nozzle extension in shape
并让它在级间段里上升时保持安全
and keeps it safe while it's inside the interstage on ascent.
发射后4分45秒
T-plus four minutes and 45 seconds.
一级火箭滑行到它的最大高度 或者说远地点
The first stage booster has coasted to its maximum altitude, or apogee,
差不多149公里的高度 然后开始掉回地球
of about 149 kilometers and begins to fall back down to earth.
发射后7分15秒
T-plus seven minutes and 15 seconds.
一级开始再入大气
The first stage begins to reenter the atmosphere
为了再入点火 它会点燃9个梅林发动机中的3个
and lights up three of its nine Merlin engines for an entry burn,
这将让它大幅减速并在剧烈的再入热中生存下来
which slows it down enough to survive the intense reentry heating.
发射后8分47秒
T-plus eight minutes 47 seconds.
二级火箭发动机关机
The second stage cuts off,
正式将龙飞船放在初始停泊轨道
officially placing the Dragon Capsule into its initial parking orbit
也就是190km x 205km的轨道 欢呼声随之到来
of 190 kilometers by 205 kilometers and cheering will ensue.
发射后8分52秒
T-plus eight minutes 52 seconds.
一级开始着陆点火
The first stage begins its landing burn
因为它准备降落到着陆垫 也就是无人自动驾驶船上
as it prepares to land on the autonomous spaceport drone ship.
发射后9分22秒
T-plus nine minutes 22 seconds.
一级着陆在无人船上 会有更强烈的欢呼声
The first stage lands on the drone ship and cheering intensifies.
发射后12分钟
T-plus 12 minutes.
载人龙飞船从二级分离
The Crew Dragon separates from the second stage.
发射后12分46秒
T-plus 12 minutes 46 seconds.
龙飞船的鼻锥打开
The nosecone of the Dragon Capsule opens,
暴露出星敏感器 并有助于导航系统
exposing the star tracker, which aides in navigation.
发射后49分6秒
T-plus 49 minutes six seconds.
在数次检查天龙座RCS和几次指向性机动后
After a few check outs of the Draco reaction control thrusters and a few pointing maneuvers,
会进行16.11m/s(速度变化量)的阶段性点火
there's a phase burn of 16.11 meters per second
来让龙飞船对准国际空间站的轨道
to align the orbits of the Dragon and the International Space Station.
发射后09:44:44
T-plus nine hours 44 minutes and 44 seconds.
还会进行另一次阶段性点火
There's another phase adjustment burn.
发射后11:10:15
T-plus 11 hours 10 minutes 15 seconds.
龙飞船会使用天龙座发动机点火44.2m/s
The Dragon Capsule performs a 44.2 meter per second burn using its Draco thrusters
以提高它的轨道 以便更加接近国际空间站
to boost its orbit closer to the International Space Station.
发射后11:55:01
T-plus 11 hours 55 minutes and one second.
还会进行另一次点火
There's another burn,
这次将会有57.89m/s
this time of 57.89 meters per second,
这将圆化轨道
which circularizes the orbit.
发射后17:40:24
T-plus 17 hours 40 minutes and 24 seconds.
经过几次中途修正点火
After a few mid-course correction burns,
龙飞船将会接近400米安全距离球体空间 或者说KOS
the Crew Dragon is approaching the 400-meter keep out sphere, or KOS,
并要求任务控制中心进行是否继续的投票
and requires a go/no-go poll from Mission Control in order to continue.
发射后17:50:24
T-plus 17 hours 50 minutes and 24 seconds.
龙飞船进入安全距离空间内 并达到0号航路点
The Dragon Capsule enters the keep out sphere and hits Waypoint Zero,
也就是国际空间站下方400米位置
which is 400 meters below the International Space Station.
发射后18:15:24
T-plus 18 hours 15 minutes 24 seconds.
龙飞船到达1号航路点
The Dragon Capsule arrives at Waypoint One
并保持大概220米的距离 准备对准对接轴方向
and holds approximately 220 meters away to align to the docking axis.
发射后18:51:24
T-plus 18 hours 51 minutes 24 seconds.
最后的是否继续的投票将决定是否对接
A final go/no-go poll is given for docking.
发射后18:56:24
T-plus 18 hours 56 minutes and 24 seconds.
龙飞船到达2号航路点
The Dragon Capsule arrives at Waypoint two,
距离缩小到仅有20米 进入到一个短暂停留阶段
which is only 20 meters away and gets placed into a short hold.
发射后19:01:24
T-plus 19 hours one minute and 24 seconds.
龙飞船离开2号航路点 并进行对接
The Dragon capsule departs Waypoint Two and goes in for the docking.
发射后19:06:25
T-plus 19 hours six minutes and 25 seconds.
乘员和任务控制中心都能松一口气
A big sigh of relief from the crew and Mission Control.
龙飞船对接完成 正式到达国际空间站
The Dragon Capsule is docked and the crew has officially arrived at the International Space Station!
这下你就看完了
So there you have it!
又好又容易对吧
Nice and easy, huh?
那么 实际上你可以通过iss-sim.spacex.com自己尝试对接
Well, you can actually try the docking yourself by going to iss-sim.spacex.com
看看你自己是否可以进行最终对接机动
and see if you can do the final docking maneuvers yourself.
这不是坎巴拉太空计划 但它还是很有趣
It's no Kerbal Space Program, but it's still really fun.
Let me know if you liked this video and
if you want me to do another one for reentry
and landing and if you want me to do a similar video
when crew rides Boeing's Starliner for the first time, too.
Be sure and let me know if you have any other questions in the comments below
and be sure and stick around because I have tons more videos coming out
that will help you understand all this cool stuff as we enter a new era of human spaceflight.
Now, if you're watching this before DM-2,
be sure and watch my live stream because I will be there at the Kennedy Space Center,
only about five kilometers away from the launch.
I'll be there pretty much all day answering your guys' questions.
Now, if you're watching this video after DM-2,
just tune in to any launch, upcoming launch.
I try to stream all of them,
or at least as many as I can.
So it's a really fun way to interact and get your questions answered live
and it's just kinda fun to hang out with everyone.
I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters for helping making videos like this possible,
but also for helping me get my butt down
to Florida to bring you guys some awesome coverage of these upcoming launches.
Now, if you want to help me maybe script
and research or get your thoughts and comments on videos before they come out
or join our exclusive Subreddit, our exclusive live streams,
and, of course, our awesome Discord channel,
which has just the best space community,
please go to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
And while you're online,
be sure and check out my awesome web store for cool merch like this brand new shirt.
This is our new Future Martian Society shirt.
It includes Arcadia Planitia and the actual landing coordinates
that is currently the prime A candidate landing site for Starship,
which I just think is super, super cool.
And also we have some (chuckles),
over here we have some reminders of the atmosphere and the gravity on Mars.
And a friendly reminder to be sure and wear your space suit when you go outside.
So maybe one of you guys will be wearing this shirt on Mars someday, but while you're online,
just check out all of my cool merchandise 'cause
this stuff does help me continually upgrade and make better and cooler videos for you guys.
So that's everydayastronaut.com/shop.
Thanks everybody, that's gonna do it for me.
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人
(hypnotic back EDM music)